Guide to the Edward Eliscu Papers TAM.270
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Edward Eliscu Papers
circa 1936-1998
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Eliscu, Edward, 1902-1998
Eliscu, David
TAM.270
1 Linear Feet in 1 record carton.
Edward Eliscu (1902-1998) was a lyricist, playwright, screenwriter, and a progressive activist in the entertainment industry, notably in Hollywood in the 1930s and 1940s. The collection includes his correspondence, scripts, speeches, articles and photographs.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials were donated by David Eliscu in 2001. The accessio numbers associated with these gifts are 2001.045, 2001.149, and NPA.2002.049.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically.
Historical/Biographical Note
Edward Eliscu (1902-1998), was a lyricist (best known for Without a Song), playwright and screen-writer, and a progressive activist in the entertainment industry, notably in Hollywood in the 1930s and 1940s.
Scope and Content Note
The Edward Eliscu Papers contain correspondence, unpublished lyrics, scripts and other literary writings (many of a political nature), copies of The Spectator, Eliscu's weekly column in the National Guardian, film, theater and general political ephemera and internal documents, including from several progressive entertainment industry organizations such as the Hollywood League for Democratic Action, the Hollywood Peace Forum, the Hollywood Anti-Nazi League for the Defense of American Democracy, the Hollywood Theatre Alliance, the Hollywood Writers Mobilization, and the Motion Picture Democratic Committee. There is also a speech, written by Eliscu for delivery by Progressive Party candidate Henry Wallace at an October 8, 1948 presidential campaign appearance in Portland, Oregon. Also included in the collection are a set of a dozen cartoons (Defending the WPA), and about a dozen photographs related to the campaign to defend blacklisted screenwriter Dalton Trumbo, and one photograph of Ann Meeropol.
Articles.; Speeches.; Correspondence.; Scripts (documents); Black-and-white photographs.; Communism -- United States.; Communism and motion pictures -- United States.; Political activists |z California |z Hollywood (Los Angeles, Calif.).; Communists -- United States.; Photographs.; Hollywood blacklist.; Eliscu, Edward, 1902-1998; Eliscu, David
- 12 Cartoons Defending WPA by Members of the American Artists Congress, circa 1936 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- American Writers Congress, 1965-1971 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Biographical, 1970-1993 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1939-1955 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1956-1975 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1976-1998 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Film, Theater, Political Ephemera, 1948-1983 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Hollywood Activism, 1942-1955 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Hollywood Inquisition, 1950-1953 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Hollywood Town Meeting (script), undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Lyrics, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
- McCarthy, Joseph, 1949-1960 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Midnight Visitor (script), undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Photographs: General, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Photographs: Hollywood 10, circa 1947 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Political Ephemera, 1940s - 1950s (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Spectator, 1954-1961 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Spectator: reviews/notes, 1954, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Sticks and Stones (program), 1938 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Sticks and Stones (script), ca.1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Theater Ephemera, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Twenty-Five Candles (script), undated (Box 1, Folder 22A)
- Virgin Voter (script), 1970 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Wallace, Henry, 1942, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- We'll Be Back (script), undated (Box 1, Folder 25)